中英字幕by:Ocean-藏心(微博)    推荐指数:★★★★☆
简介: 深入剖析了RecyclerView中最核心的布局管理器部分,
也捎带讲解了RecyclerView的其他机制,看完之后,你会真正明白为何ListView要被废弃.
精通RecyclerView布局
Mastering RecyclerView Layouts
你好,他好,大家好
hello hello everyone
进来,坐好,我要开始讲了.下午好
come sit stay awhile good afternoon
今天大家过的如何?噢,大家的答案我喜欢听
how's everyone today the that's what I like to hear
我叫大卫-史密斯,我是NewCircle培训中心的Android老大
I hello everyone my name is Dave Smith I am the Android lead for new circle training
我们对很多技术做开源的培训,Android只是其中一项
we do open Source Training a number of technologies and reduce happens to be one of them
不过言归正传,今天我要谈的主题是
I'm gonna be here to you today to talk about
精通RecyclerView的布局.
我们的关注点不在于如何具体的
mastering recycler view layouts I we're not gonna talk more specifically about
具体的使用RecyclerView
how to use recycler view
而在于如何
in the generals a sense today we're going to be talking mostly about building
自定义RecyclerView的布局管理器
custom layout managers with recyclerView
以及我们在自定义布局管理器过程中
应该注意的事情
and how we can kind of get through that process so
先给大家说说我站在这儿的原因
a little bit about why I'm here standing in front of you today
正所谓前人栽树,后人乘凉嘛
call it a bit of (Hannah) a humanitarian
effort
我会给你介绍你可能需要到的工具(指API的帮助类)
I'm really here to give you the tools
hopefully that you will need
当你尝试使用RecyclerView时,当你为了特定的需求
if you are trying to use recycler view
you're trying to customize it for your
而去自定义RecyclerView时将有所帮助
specific purposes
我会尽力带你把这整个过程走通
and trying to get you through that
process with out losing
来让你少走弯路
you know essentially losing your mind
I'm so
在我们深入讲解之前,我想确保大家是不是都在一个级别上
before we dive too deep into the details
I just wanna make sure that everybody's on the same page so
那么大家所看到的这种情况是从哪儿来的呢
where does this all this come from you
know the
众所周知,视图回收的这种主意是一种惯用的技术,
this idea of view recycling is a
pattern that's used in mobile all over
其被用于所有的移动平台
the place all mobile platforms do this
android恰好是其中一个而已.
android just happens to do it as well
it has done this
从android1.0就有了,说具体点,这种机制体现在
since version 1 I  most specifically
LisView这个控件上.想必各位都用过不下百十次吧
in the format ListView most of us have
probably use a number of times
我只是好奇,请举下手.各位都有谁真的尝试着
I am just curious shorthand how many
have you have actually tried to use
去用RecyclerView呢
recycler view
还不错嘛.那么,有谁试着去写自定义的布局管理器呢
before,pretty good.how many have you tried to
build your own layout manager
貌似人不多咯.不过超过我的预期咯
okay more than I expected good
其实更重要的是,各位的头发都还在.这比啥都好啊.
and mostly you still have your hair
that even better so
这种对视图的回收利用机制使我们
this this idea view recycling is really
it allows developers and it allows
的设备能够
devices to
展现非常大的数据集合,可能是成百上千条
present large collections of data
maybe hundreds or even thousands of
的数据项
items
给用户.但又仅仅用有限的几个视图便可完成
to the user but only using a handful of
views
不必创建跟数据项个数一样多的视图来展示数据
not creating as many views as we need to
display that data
作为替代,使用一种叫做 回收->绑定 的过程
but instead, using a process called
recycling of rebinding
来将用户需要看到的数据绑定到各个视图之上
of data to individual views as the
user needs to see them
可以这么讲,
so basically like we've got going here
we have this idea that
显示用户数据集的视图的个数
the number reviews necessary to show the
user their collection
只等于我们屏幕上能显示出的视图的个数
is only what we need to be able to show
on screen
一旦用户开始跟他的数据集交互,不管是上划
and as the user is interacting with this
content whether there's scrolling up
还是怎么划
around
只要视图被划出屏幕,这个视图就不需要了.但是
as view scroll off-screen they're no
longer necessary but rather than
对于将要到来的新的数据,不采用创建一个新视图的方式
creating new views for the new data
coming in
而是把这个旧的视图重新填充数据
we can simply take the old views
repurpose them with new data
平移其到一个新位置,然后让它划入屏幕即可
shift them to a new location and allow
them to slide back n
因此,用这种办法,才使得我们能够展示成百上千的数据项
so that way we can display hundreds of
thousands of items
仅仅使用有限的几个视图.大体上,
with only a handful of views. generally
you're gonna see you
你会发现RecyclerView和ListView需要创建的视图个数
recycler views or list views creating as
many viewers as necessary to display on
会比展示在屏幕上的视图的个数多一两个
screen plus maybe one or two more
这跟采用的算法有关.
depending on how the algorithm works
okay
再重申一次,我不会讲太多如何使用RecyclerView
so again I'm not gonna talk too much
about how to use recycler view I think
这方面有很好的文档
there's some good documentation on that
but
RecyclerView的精华在于
the basics have recycler view is that
recycler view is a
RecyclerView是对这种机制的革新,更加灵活易用
more flexible,evolution of this
pattern
其允许我们来对可复用的集合创建
that allows us to create these
recyclable collections in
各种自定义(布局,动画,装饰)的实现.之前,我们只有ListView
all kinds of custom implementations you
know previously we only had list view
是一个可在垂直方向上滚动的列表
which was a vertical scrolling list
开发者们已经为其做过一些自定制的实现了
there have been some custom
implementations done by other developers
比方说水平滚动的列表.等等其他定制的效果
ways to do this maybe horizontally
or another custom ways
RecyclerView为之前大家所需要的实现提供了一个框架
recyclerView bring that all together
into a framework so because it that
因此,要想使用RecyclerView
recycler you cannot be used
你必须要提供一个布局管理器不可.这俩必须成对使用,不然
without a layout manager.the two always
have to pair together in fact if you try
当你尝试实例化一个没有定义布局管理器的RecyclerView时
to instantiate a RecyclerView without
a layup manager
你会得到一个没有用的异常,会让你的程序崩溃
you'll get a very unhelpful exception about
that will crash your application
所以,用RecyclerView之前,咱一定要有布局管理器
OK.so you always need to set a layout
manager before you try to use a recycler
view
为了使你能登堂入室,或者说为了便于应对最常用的场合
and to sort of get you started or cover
most use cases
框架在这方面干的很不错.为我们提供了
the framework has done a pretty good job
of providing
几个自带的布局管理器.在大多数情况下,你甚至有可能
a handful of its own layout managers that
in a lot cases you might even be able
都用得上
to use wholesale
如果你从Lpreview或者从RecyclerView最初版本发布以来
and if you haven't looked at recycler
view since the L reviewer or maybe since
你一直都没有再看RecyclerView的话
some of the initial releases
你可能会漏掉几个他们目前已经加进去的布局管理器
you may have missed some of the layout
managers they've added
因为,预览版的时候,我们手里的RecyclerView
because during the preview really all we
所提供的基本功能就跟ListView差不多
had was some basic functionality that
was very similar to ListView and they
但是到正式发布的时候,很多新功能都已经被加进去了.
add it quite a bit by the time they got
to release
接下来,我来快速梳理一遍,framework提供了些什么
let's just quickly go through what the
framework gives us the first
首先,是大家都很熟悉的
option which will.familiar to
probably most of you
LinearLayoutManager.
is the linear layout manager so the
LinearLayout manager
你基本可以把它当成ListView的替代品
is essentially the ListView replacement
if you well
尽管它还有些其他的特性,但是基本上它是
I it's got some additional features in
it but is it is a
一个列表项均分的单一列表.LinearLayoutManager有个
uniform single list of items.one of the
neat features
ListView没有的特性.那就是对方向参数的可选性
of linear layout manager that we
didn't have in listview is the optional
那就是对方向参数的可选性
orientation setup
因此LinearLayoutManager允许RecyclerView创建可滚动的列表
so LinearLayout Manager allows recycler
view to create a list of items that scrolls
不管是垂直的还是水平的.很明显,我们之前
either vertically or horizontally which
is a new feature that we obviously
是没有这个特性的.
didn't have before
你只需要在LinearLayoutManager实例化的时候
and this is controlled during the
instantiation of the LinearLayout
指定水平或者垂直的方向参数即可
manager just by giving it that vertical
or horizontal orientation qualifier there
这里最后一个boolean型的参数,代表是你是否要逆序进行布局
OK. the boolean parameter that at the end that allows you to also reverse the layout
通常,大家都是把它设为false
so the traditional by setting it to
false would
那么列表项显示的顺序跟适配器中getView()顺序是一致的
order the items as they viewed in the
adapter so
从位置0开始,由高到低依次依序显示列表项
adapter item position $0 upfront down to
the end
如果你把这个参数设成true,那么就成逆序了.
if you set this parameter to true it
will reverse that and have the
列表中最后一项会先显示.因此,从前ListView的这种特性
end of the adapter show first in the
list okay so they have that feature in
在LinearLayoutManager中也存在
there as well
接下来,framework提供给我们的是GridLayoutManager
the next one that we have appears the
grid layout manager
这个布局管理器在L预览版中是没有的,但是其功能性
so this is...this one was not in the
preview but functionality have it is
我们却不陌生.因为我们都知道GridView
still pretty intuitive to most of us because
we've either seen or used gridview before
当然,这里的布局管理器更加灵活一点.它的特点是,
at a little bit more flexible than that
but the idea here is that
大体上,我们仍有着均分的网格布局列表项集合
we're still having this uniform
collection of items
但是这些列表项,现在可以一个挨着一个填满一行后,
but these items can now be stacked up
uh you know, either side by side on
再竖着往上填(- -!)
top of each other
像LinearLayoutManager一样,GridLayoutManager也提供
uh, just like with linear layout manager
grid layout manager does support
方向参数,因此我们可以像之前一样,做个垂直的可滚动列表
orientation changes so we can do a
vertical scrolling list
也可以做一个水平的可滚动网格列表
like the traditional grid view or we can
flip that into a horizontally scrolling grid
这里位于参数列表中的数字代表着
instead now the the number that you see
in this
GridLayoutManager所提供的一种控制参数
declaration here is that the the grid
layout manager supports
这个参数决定了每行item所能占用的最大span数
controlling how many what they call
spans are associated with that
每个数据项都有着相关的span数
particular item
这里把这个参数称作span而不是行或列的原因在于
now the reason they call them spans
instead of rows or columns is because
GridLayoutManager有着两种方向
the fact that you can do it
简单的讲,span定义了
in either direction so a span just simply
defines
你能够在某一维度上堆栈起来的item数,纵表即为列数
how many items you can stack up so in a
vertical grid the spans are the columns
横表即为行数
in a horizontal grid the span to be the
Rose
除此之外,span还
OK but they're still defined in such a
way that they are uniform so
仍旧体现其均匀的特性.举例来讲,在这我定义了2个span
for instance in this case I have two
spans defined so
这里每行就被均分成了两部分来给列表项占用.仅用span
they will evenly be spaced on both sides
there's not really a mechanism to define
是无法将每行不均等分的(左边占1/3 右边占2/3).
you know sort of a 1/3 2/3 with the
spans
你一定是在这个控制水准啦,懂么?但是别怕,有哥在呢.
you're necessarily at this level ok
they did at a
系统的确提供了一个相当有意思的特性,
来让你对均等性进行改变
fairly interesting feature though that
allows you to change the uniformity
这显然比传参数复杂一点,我们要用SpanSizeLook
in in some basic ways using something
called a span size lookup
我这里的例子中,GridLayoutManager的span依然
so in the example that I have here the
grid layout manager still has
被设置为2,但是我们自定义了SpanSizeLookUp的实现
two spans defined but using this custom
implementation of
我们在运行时为
a span size lookup we can define at
runtime for
每个位置来设置其占用span的个数
each individual position how many spans
我这的方法挺简单
should each item take up and this is a
very simple algorithm basically says
每个3的倍数的列表项都会占用2个span
every third item should take two spans
而其他的就还按默认的,只占用一个
and all the other should take just the
default 1
这里,大家所看到的,就是这种实现的效果
and this gives us the implementation
that we see up here
这样网格就被整行分割了
where every other row is essentially
laid out
这样网格就被整行分割了
all the way across but the grids
interspersed in between
因此你可以在GridLayoutManager里创建一些变形的元素
so you can create some shifting elements
here
但是这必须被定义在可用的span数之上
but this is always defined in terms of
the number of spans available
因此,这不像明显的像素宽度或其他测量参数
so this isn't like a an explicit pixel
width or anything like that you define
你必须提前定义好在你的布局中要用到的span数
ahead a time how many spans are
available
然后,你可以用LookUp来决定
in this layout and then you can use the
lookup to basically tell it how many of
(在桌子上占用的单元数)
those you think of them as the cells in a
table
这个特定的item所应该占用的单元数
this specific item should take up at I
关于GridLayoutManager还有件事你不能忘
it one of the important things to
realize with grid layout though is that the
不论其使用何种的方向.其表项的高度
whatever orientation it's in,the item
height:
亦或其表项的宽度(水平方向),在每个表项
or for towards on all the item with
still needs to be uniform for
所占的块中必须是均等的.在我们这个例子中,
each element block so for instance in
this example
每一行中的item的高度必须是一样的
all the items in the same row have to be
the same height
行高取决于
and the the row height itself will
最高的列表项的高度
essentially adjust to whatever the
tallest item is
因此,如果我在一行中间的元素比两边的元素高
so if I had one item in the middle of the
other two that was much taller
那么两边的元素下面就会有留白
there would be a gap underneath the two
items on either side
位于其下面的元素并不会滑上去填充空隙
they don't slide up to sort of fill in
the gaps or anything like that
而你恰好正是为了这种目的
for that
别怕,我们还有StaggeredGridLayoutManager.
we have the staggered grid layout
manager
因此,SGLM正是构建在这种模式之上的
so the staggered grid layout manager
build on that pattern
其被构造的方法和布局的操作都跟GLM相似
and operates and is constructed in a
very similar way to grid layout manager
不同的是,我们有机会去为表项视图定义
but in this case we have the opportunity
to define
不同的大小.然后SGLM会把将其布局出来
different size item views and the
staggered grid layout manager will simply lay them out
并尽其所能的将留白用item填充起来.
as best it knows how underneath each
other filling in those individual gaps
对我们的实现来讲
OK the from an implementation perspective
创建这个布局管理器跟创建前面两个一样
creating one is again no different then
working with the other two and it
这种管理器也同样支持水平和垂直
also supports horizontal and vertical
orientation
前方依旧高能
now
有件事要注意,我刚刚所展示给你们的每一种布局管理器
one of the things to notice
about each of these that I've shown you
它们都支持不同方向的滚动
so far is that well they support
different orientations of scrolling
但是,无论何时这些实现只能支持一条坐标轴上的滚动
both these implementations only supports
growing in a single axis
我想要做的是
at any given time what what I need to do
创造一种RecyclerView,就说它是个简单的网格布局吧
if I wanted to create a recycler view
implementation or say like a simple grid
我想让它能在两个方向上都能滚动
that I want to be able to actually
scroll in two directions
我能这么做么?答案是,你可以的.
不过在framework里,你找不到现成的
can I do that? well the answer is yes
the framework is not gonna give you anything to do that
这就要靠我们自己动手来创建布局管理器了
in that case we have to look may be perhaps building our own
那么我会向你展示我所干过的活
so what I've done and I'll show you the
在我们会谈结束后,你可以自己去分析源码
where you can look at the example at the end of the talk here
可以说我所做的研究就是现在所谈的问题的核心
is a sort of key study for what what
we're talking about here
首先,经过我全面的分析之后,我决定去创建
I went through and decided I'm gonna
create a
一个二维的可滚动的布局,这是个简单均分网格布局
two-dimensional scrolling layout this
just a simple uniform grid
网格里的元素会一个挨着一个的布局出来,其中元素的位置
OK so the grid is going to be laid out
the positions would basically be the way
就是你在屏幕上所看到的
you see them up there whether
元素的顺序是从左到右,网格的宽度是固定的
they order themselves left to right the
grid with is fixed
因此元素按列数被包裹起来,按行从上往下排
so the number of columns they just wrap around
to the next and I'll just line themselves up
这就好像我正在看一个电视预告或者是体育赛事比分
like if I was looking at maybe a TV
schedule or sports scores in a grid
或者其他诸如此类的东西
something like that
用户可以随意的上滑下滑左滑右滑斜着划
then the user could simply pan and
scroll around
按任意方向滑动去查看网格列表中的内容
this content visually in whatever
orientation they wanted
我最先给自己提出的问题是
okay and the question essentially I pose
to myself was
我能用RecyclerView来干这件事儿么?或者换一个说法
can I build this with recycler view and
come out saying on the other side
好吧,想不出来别的说法了.等你听我讲完就该明白了
I'll let you decide when I'm done
whether know that actually words okay
在我阐述你所需的,构建这种RecyclerView的方法之前
before I talk about the mechanisms of
what you need to do to build this
咱们先来谈谈RecyclerView内部的一些机制
let's discuss a little bit about
the internals
来帮你理解
of RecyclerView you so that you can get
some idea of
文档中你可能遇到过的一些方法的流程梳理
how these pieces that you may see in the
documentation actually fit together
首先我想讲的是
so the first element that i wanna talk
about in the
RecyclerView给我们的一个核心帮助类
the core utility if you will that
recycler view
这个类体现了回收利用的概念
gives you is this instance for this
concept a recycler
在构建自定义布局管理器的时候,这个类干的活挺多的
this is really the workhorse of
building a custom layout the recycler
回收器(recycler)是RecyclerView传递给你的
is a utility given to you by a recycler
view
它为你干了几乎所有的
that does all of the work necessary
for
像获取视图,缓存视图,等等
obtaining views cacheing views your
basically doing all the recycling
所有跟回收相关的活
functionality that you need
它让你能够快速的获取一个新视图来填充新数据.
以及快速丢弃
to be able to quickly get new views for
new data and toss away views you don't
你不再需要的视图
need anymore
因此,当你开始构建一个布局管理器时,
OK so when you're building a layout
manager your interaction is almost
你的交互行为跟
exclusively
recycler息息相关.比方说,当你需要一个新的视图时
with the recycler there you know when
when you need a new view
当用户滑动屏幕到下一个位置时,有新视图进入等等
with the next position the user is
scrolling enter a view or something like
新进入的视图就是从recycler中返回的
that you obtain that view from the
recycler
你只要告诉recycler你所需新视图的position
by giving it the position value that you
want so this is the next position I need
那么recycler就会返回一个已经绑定过相关数据的新视图
please give me the view that has all the
data already bound associated with it
类似地,当你的滑动一些视图移出屏幕时,
and similarly when you're done with a
view but say it scrolls of screen and
这些视图你已经不再需要了
you don't need it anymore
你应该把这些视图丢给recycler,以便于
you would toss that back to the recycler
so that it can
将来使用的时候还能从recycler中获取到,
并且获取到的是已经绑定好数据的
keep access to that around and rebind it
to some other data later and headed back
(同上)
to another point
所有的这些工作都在recycler内部完成.
okay so all that functionality is bound
inside the recycler in the recyclers job
recycler的对外的工作是对接adapter.
而adapter是你所有数据的来源
is to talk to the adapter so the adapter
were all your data comes from where you
你在adapter里根据数据源创建ViewHolder和绑定数据
you create view holders and bind all the
data that
recycler是可以直接从adapter中
is ... there's a direct interaction
between the recycler in the adapter to
获取所需信息的
get all that information
但是,布局管理器就不同,你该谨记,布局管理器绝不该
the key point to remember here is your
layout manager should never
去引用适配器
ever ever touch the adapter
因为这个工作是recycler干的.
当你正在创建一个布局管理器时
that is the recyclers job if you have
are building a layout manager that
出于某种原因,你非要获取一些状态信息的话或者
一些其他跟列表项相关的数据时
somehow you was trying to get state
information or some other data directly
(从适配器中)
from the adapter
你会把事情搞砸.然而,对于状态信息的存取,
其实用ViewHolder才最合适不过
that pattern is broken instead the view
holders
在RecyclerViewAPI里,ViewHolder被强制传递给你
that are basically forced down your
throat by the recycler view API
它才是你存取状态的最佳选择.因为
those are great places to hold that
state because the adapter
不光适配器可以获取到ViewHolder,布局管理器也能
has access to the view holder and so
does the layout manager
它俩能获取到VH(ViewHolder)的原因在于,
中间者recycler在内部也对VH进行了状态信息的存取
and recycler view does this internally
you know, all the information that
每个位置上的视图都应该知道其相关的状态信息
view knows about its current position
这些状态信息包含其是否正在被改变,是否被删除或添加
whether it's are changing weather is
being added removed all these things that
当RecyclerView对所管理的视图进行好看的动画时,
recycler view uses for these fancy
transition animations
这些状态信息都是从ViewHolder中存取的.
你可以继承ViewHolder来对自定义的状态信息进行存取
that state is all held on the beholder
and you can extend that the holder which
当然,当你构建自己适配器,系统也要求你这么做.
your obviously supposed to when you
build your own adapter so if you wanna
因此,当你需要为每个视图设置一些状态信息的话
stuff more state in there for each
individual view
正确的做法就是继承ViewHolder来干这事儿.
因为视图会携带着这些信息
that's the right way to do that and then
that will transport along with the views
当其被传递到布局管理器中时.
as they move into the layout manager and
and so on and so forth
因此牢记,布局管理器只对接回收器,不对接适配器
so always touch the recycler never touch
the adapter
接下来,咱们对recycler的讨论要再深入一点
alright so let's look a little bit
deeper into the recycler itself so I
我之前提到的
mention that the recycler
recycler最核心的工作就是其对视图的缓存(回收利用)
is a it's a caching mechanism above all
else
一方面,你要从recycler中获取新视图
so the recycler is where you need to get
new views
另一方面,你还要把废弃视图丢给recycler,但结果是,
and you need to toss away your old views
but it turns out that they actually have
recycler里面竟有两种级别的机制
a two-level mechanism inside
来干这两件事情.recycler中有个叫废料堆的概念
to make this work the recycler has this
concept of what they call the scrap heap
它底层还有个叫回收池的东西
and then underneath that is this idea of
the recycle poor
这两者之间的差别是很微小的.在多数情况下其影响
now the the difference between them is
fairly nuanced and in a lot cases it doesn't
可以忽略不计.不过,如果你致力于获取最佳性能时
really matter but there are some
optimizations that can be made if you
了解这种微小差别就很有必要了
understand the difference
这里的ScrapHeap就像是第一道防线,
the the scrap heap is usually the the
first line of defense where you would
当你在Layout的时候
typically toss views
通常会把视图先丢到那里面去.难理解,没关系.先听着.
while you're doing layouts and all I'll
explain to you in sort of a technique how
后面我会配着代码给你讲.
ScrapHeap是一种轻量级的操作
you would possibly use that in your code but the
scrap heap is a is a very lightweight place
在它里面检索视图和丢弃视图
where views can be tossed and retrieved
back
是以一种很快的方式进行.
甚至从中获取的视图都不用再重新绑定数据
in a in a very quick fashion often cases
without even having to rebind the data
作为一个布局管理器,是很适合用这种结构来存取视图的
so it it's a nice place that as a layout
manager
你可以把一些暂时不想用的视图先丢给ScrapHeap
you can toss a bunch of views that you
know you're going to reuse again
注意这些视图还是可见的,然后也许在你对整个列表视图
采用一些转换操作后,再让那些被丢弃的视图回来时
they're still on screen but maybe you
need to shift them around or something
这时,这些回来的视图可以不走适配器(重新生成,绑定数据)这条路
like that and rather than them having to
go back to the adapter to rebind data
传回给你,而是
and bring them back to you
你可以直接从ScrapHeap中拿到你之前丢弃给它的视图
you can just quickly get them back
from the scrap heap
再然后,你再对这些视图进行一下布局,
那么你对列表的转换操作就算完美的结束了
因此,通常,咱都是先用ScrapHeap来丢掉视图的.
and lay them out again,so typically
you'll toss things in the scrap heap
不过如果你确定某些视图你永远都不用了的话,
那么就该RecyclerPool派上用场了
first the recycle pool is more commonly
used for views you are certain you don't
(同上)
need anymore
比方说,当你运行了一次Layout之后,你可能有一些
so for instance after you've run a
layout maybe you have a handful of
视图滑出了屏幕,以及你知道
views that have scrolled off screen and
you didn't
你不想再使用这些视图了.
那么你就可以把这些视图扔给RecyclerPo
you didn't need these and you know that
you can toss those into the recycle poor
RecyclerPool依然可以被认为,你能从中快速获取视图
the recycle pool is still a quick way
of allowing you to get data back
但是,你所获取到的视图的一些meta-data会丢失
but it tosses away some of the
additional meta-data
它仅仅对ViewHolder以及里面的itemView进行一下缓存
basically recycles the view holder and
keeps the view around so
尽管你知道它可以快速的从适配器中重新绑定数据
even know it can quickly rebind data
from the adapter its a little bit more
但是如果你对每个视图都这么操作的话,代价就有点高了
expensive if you're constantly doing
that for every single view
所以,通常你是把确定不会再在回收器中使用的视图
so typically you would wanna throw views
you know you don't need in recycle into
丢给RecyclePool
the recycle poor
其他的那就是都扔给ScrapHeap.我会给你展示
toss everything else in this Scrap Heap
and I'll show you a technique that kind of
如何具体地去干这些事
allows you to do this
分别针对这两种级别.接下来,我要讲解的概念是
on on two different levels.the other
concepts that
detachment和removal的区别
we were illustrating here is the
difference between a detachment and a
(同上)
removal
这里看到的方法都是绑到一起的
in the method that I've got appear
that they look like they're bound
但是你也可以将方法拆分着用
together but you can actually do all
these operations separately you can
attach() 和 detach()
attach and detach
remove() 和 scrap(),所以你可以单个调用,
绑定在一起只是为了方便
remove scrap you can do those things
individually these are just convenience
(同上)
functions
在我看来,这里的函数命名是有点臭的
that the syntax is a little stinky in my
opinion because
因为detach是跟scrap相对应的
detach is really.it's a mechanism
similar to scrapping
当你把一个视图暂时的丢弃时
that allows you to toss a view away
temporarily
这个视图你知道你会在相同的布局过程中重用
that you know you're going to reuse in
the same layout pass
尽管这里的名字是detach
so the while the name is detach
从专业的角度来看,被detach的视图没有在父视图中被移除
a detached view is not technically
removed from its parent
这里的父视图是指RecyclerView.
子视图仍被添加在父视图中的
which is the recycler view it's actually
still added to that view
其实布局管理器只允许你对这个视图进行一点操作而已
the layout managers just allowed to
manipulate it a little bit so it's much
因此detach其实是个相当轻量级的操作
more lightweight
矛盾的是虽然名字是detach,但是还是attach着父视图的
I but it is still attached to the parent
view
remove操作跟你在ViewGroup中的移除视图操作相似
remove view is very similar to of a
view removal you would have on
这里被remove的视图可是的的确确的从其
a view group or anything like that
where it is actually detached from its
父视图中移除了
parent so it's
这让我不爽的就是remove操作的视图的确是detached,
但是detach操作的视图却不是的
its little bit difficult cause remove
actually detach and detach does not
这里的话,你把detach当成一种轻量级的操作,而remove
but you can really think of it as
detaches the lightweight and remove is
就是一种重量级的操作.这样来理解就比较好了
the heavyweight
通常你会把这两种事情合并在一起来做
so typically in most cases you do these
things together
在recycler中的detachAndScrap方法
so the method on a recycler for detachAndScrap
被用来丢弃可能再次用到的视图
is where you would you would use that
to toss views away that you
而removeAndRecycle丢弃掉的视图,
might use again and removeAndRecycler
is the one you would use to toss views a
当你下次再从中获取时,可能就不一样了
away that the next time you need it.it's
probably gonna be for different
因此这两个方法被用在不同的场合
different use case or a different mind
一些其他的
okay couple other
小贴士.这些小贴士在自定义布局管理器时肯定用得到
tips just to know when you're building a
layout manager
布局管理器顾名思义,它的作用就是负责measure和layout
layout manager as the name implies is
responsible for measuring and laying out
RecyclerView中每个视图
every view in a recycler view
这个作用跟ViewGroup对待其孩子视图的作用相类似
very similar to the responsibility that
a container view group has for it
(同上)
child views
但是,RecyclerView还提供了个
however recycler provides this
额外的特性叫Decorations.大家都有谁用过Decoration
additional feature to developers call
decorations how many of you used decorations before
很不错呢,这个特性让你能够
okay pretty good group.they allow you to
provide
做额外的绘制或者做额外的边距间隔
或者额外的尺寸大小
additional drawing or additional margins
or sizing requirements
在每个单一的列表项之上.例如,有了列表装饰
on individual items so for instance with
an item decoration
你不仅能在视图里面定义边距,还能把边距定义在装饰里
I can define not in the item view itself
but in a declaration that
比方说如果你在decoration设置了边距
all of my items should have a margin
around them and it just
那么RecyclerView就会把这种设置应用到所有元素之上
recycler view applies that for me I
don't have to do anything with it
而对布局管理器来讲,它不用关心
and that's true on the layout side as well
I don't have to necessarily know that
当它进行布局的时候
when I lay something out
它不用把视图的边距考虑在内,API已经帮我们算好了
it has a margin and I've inside it the
API handles that part for you
前提是你要在布局的时候使用
but it only handles that part if you lay
them out appropriately using
一组不同的方法,这些方法你可能很熟悉,如果你之前做过
a different set of methods and you might
be familiar with if you've done custom
自定义布局的话
you work in the past
与你之前做自定义布局类似,用view本身的参数来布局
so similarly all the information about
the view
从技术上来说都是错误的
is technically wrong if you ask the view
itself
比方说我使用视图的left,right,top,bottom来布局的话
if I asked the view for its information
like it left right top bottom
这样做是错的,因为这些参数并没有把"装饰"考虑在内
those are incorrect because they don't
account for the decoration
作为替代,我们使用的是装饰过的left,right,top,bottom
instead there are decorated left right
top bottom
请使用这些参数来对你的视图进行布局
that will give you the appropriate value
might need while you're laying out other views
例如,我以垂直线性的方式来布局一堆视图时
so for instance if I'm laying out a
bunch views in a linear fashion
我会使用被装饰过的top和bottom值来确定前一个
I would use the decorated top and bottom
values to know where the previous view
视图的位置,以确定下一个视图的布局位置
was so I can lay out the next one in
front of it or something like that
与之相似的,我们还有新的关于获取视图大小的方法
similarly we have method like that for
sizing
被装饰过的高度和宽度同样会将视图的边距计算在内
so the decorated height and with will
account for those margins as well
我之前提到过,当你用布局管理器layout你的视图时
and as I mentioned when you're laying out your views
你要确保所用的是管理器中的layout和measure方法
you need to make sure to use the layout
and measure methods on the manager
你要去调用子视图自身的measure和layout方法
not calling measure and layout directly
on the child views
如果你没有这么干的话
okay this will if you don't do these
things
你的实现没有使用decoration的话
and you have an implementation that
doesn't use decoration
那么看起来是没啥问题的.但假如有人对其设置的适配器
it'll look like it's working but as soon
as someone brings in an adapter that has
有装饰的话
a decoration
你的布局看起来就会让人困惑了,你可能还不知道为什么
attach to it,all your layouts will be confused you won't know why
所以,只要你坚持使用这些正确的方法在布局中
so as long as you stick to using these
methods in your layouts all the time
那么你的布局管理器就会工作的非常好,
无论是否有人对其设置Decoration
it'll just work regardless of whether
somebody decorated their content or not
接下来我要讲的是
so the next piece that I wanna talk to you
被我称作为fill技术的概念
about is a concept that I call the "fill" technique
framework中关于视图回收的机制都用到fill这个概念
this is how the framework typically does
a view recycling they did it this way
不光ListView中有,布局管理器的核心实现
in ListView they do it this way in their
core
也用到了这个重要概念
layout managers as well
fill其实是一个函数,其目的是希望能够帮助你简化
this is a function that hopefully will helpful simplify the concept of
如何去运行一次布局的概念.
和如何去构建一个布局管理器的概念
how you run a layout and how you sort of build a layout manager,it is all centrally
这两个过程的核心都在于这个被称为fill的概念上.fill其实
focused around this concept called the fill the fill is really just a layout
只是个布局操作.很多操作都被封装进了这一个操作中.
operation but it's all encapsulated into
比如说对当前视图状态进行检查的操作,
this functionality that is able to check for the current state
以及对这些状态做"解释"的操作等等.通常你得自己
and account for differences in that sort
of thing.so typically what she'll have
写一个方法,当你决定用fill这项技术时
when you're using this technique is a single method that you write
因为RecyclerView并没有给你提供fillGap或者fillAxe方法
there's no fill gap or fill axe method
that lives in recycler view
这就需要我们自己来写一个方法.为了方便,就叫做fill了
you would create an internal method that we just by convention would call fill
(高能预警,我怕解释的不清楚,请把当前的布局管理假设为StaggerGridLayoutManager)这个方法会做列举出来的事情.它首先要
that does these things that I've listed here.so it's going to be responsible for
根据运行这次布局前的状态,来找出布局后第一个
determining based on the current layout what is the first
可见元素的位置
visible position you can see.you know,the
根据列表被向下滚动过长度
based on how far down the list is scrolled
由于布局前后第一个可见视图的位置会变
你要在fill中做的就是,找出布局后第一个可见视图的位置
the first visible view doesn't necessarily mean
我们的做法就是
the first visible position but you basically the idea is to enumerate all
对布局前的视图进行枚举
those individual views
根据视图的状态,
来决定哪个视图会是布局后的第一个可见视图
and figure out based on the views I have
what's the first position I can see
它可能是位置0,也可能是位置5,还可能是其他
as position 0 or as position 5 whatever
the case may be
对于此视图,我们还要找出其偏移量
and you'll typically wanna look at that view and also determine its offset
如果此视图进行过位置变换的话.
这种变化可能是由于视图被向上或向下平移了
is the view shifted in any way as it's shifted up or it's shifted down
而作为偏移量的另一部分,你还要考虑到
and as part of that,placement to that view
需不需要把Gap给计算在内.
do I have a gap?you know have the views
如果用户的滑动操作将列表往下平移到
shifted because of the user input user scroll the operation
需要其他视图进入来填充列表顶部的程度
to the point where I've got some extra
space at the top that I need to fill
那这偏移量就要算上顶部的留白(Gap)
with another view
Gap这个术语就是这样而来的
that's kinda where the term comes from
if I don't
当然,如果列表按其他方式被平移,结果如果造成下面留白
or you know and maybe it shifted the
other way and maybe I have a gap at the bottom
因此底部要有东西来填充,这样偏移量就要算上底部留白
and I need to fill something there
简而言之,fill过程分为以下几步:
1.找到第一个可视元素位置2.计算出Gap
so basically it's discovering what's
first finding gaps
不管Gap处在哪个边缘或者哪个角落
where where ever which edge whichever
corner they may live in
3.最后,把所有视图Scrap掉,丢给recycler.
这简单的三步走战略,能解决很多令人头疼的问题
and then scrapped everything this is the
part that will save you a bunch of headache
笨方法是,判断当前的状态,搞清楚视图将要如何被转换
rather than trying to determine your
current state figure out whether based
接着对各个视图都做各做各的处理.
两种方法,孰难孰易,孰好孰坏,不言自明.
on if it shifted this way do this if
it shifted that way do that just get
兄弟,你就省省劲,按我说的.1.找到第一个可视元素的位置
your current state information about
first visible position and where it
2.找出其偏移量3.把视图都留给ScrapHeap
is offset located toss everything in
this crap in
这样以来
OK then from there
咱就能利用第一个可视视图的位置和偏移量等初始信息
take that initial information of the
first view and the first location
来走一次布局的过程了.这次的布局过程的逻辑是and run a layup pass.just whatever logic
从初始位置的视图开始布局,依次往后布局,
直到后面没有剩下空间为止you need to say from this position until
I run out of space
期间不断的从recycler中取出视图,然后对视图进行layout
grab views from the recycler and laid
them out and then in that case it
这整个layout pass中,你无须考虑哪个视图是第一个,
以及后面的视图离第一个视图的距离有多远
doesn't matter what's first or how far it is
你要做的,就仅仅是把所需的所有视图拿出来
you always just fill the space with
填充完剩下的空间而已,而不必考虑
all the views that you
need depending on no matter what state
你当前列表所处什么状态
you're currently in
根据Gap所在的部位,你可能还要做一些调整的工作
now depending on where your gaps are you
might have to make some adjustments
例如,你将列表向下平移了,那么Gap就在列表的上面
so for an instance if you shift the views
down that gap is above
你将要进行布局的第一个视图的位置就
your first visible position that you
actually to lay out
往前递减了1次.
因此你要根据Gap来做一些调整工作
has popped back one.so you may need to
make some adjustment based on the gaps
不过,当你有了这些初始的信息之后
but once you have that initial information
往后列表发生任何转换,都只需执行一次三步走即可
and you scrap everything.just run a layout every time
整个操作的花费并不昂贵.
因为其中大多数视图都是被布局过的.
right it's not expensive because a lot of these views are already laid out so
再次调用layout并不会改变任何属性
calling layout again doesn't change any other properties
除此之外,我们是把视图给放在ScrapHeap中的
and in it,in addition we've tossed them
in the scrap heap
因此,将视图从recycler中检索回来的代价也是很低的
so retrieving them back from the
recycler is also very cheap
所以,可以看出来,这种操作就算不停的被执行
okay so I can do this over and over and
over again and as you know it doesn't
它也不会很影响性能.因此,我们不必想着
it doesn't necessarily affect the performance.I don't just have to try and
1.怎么对所需的空间里的元素进行操作
2.怎么调整其余的元素不受影响
manipulate the spaces that I need and
try to leave all the other views along
你如果这么干的话,你会处处碰壁,举步维艰
you'll get yourself caught in way too
many edge cases if you do that
正确的做法,就是简化整个过程,
每次更新列表都按我刚说的办
you can simplify it by just doing the
same process every time
fill这个方法不管是在初始化布局时
and then this method will be called
whether it's in initial layout
还是在用户滚动列表时,
还是在RecyclerView有任何状态改变时
where they were scrolling whether any
state changes on the recycler view which
其都会被调用.而且每次被调用所走的都是同一个过程
is gonna go through this exact same
process
(太佩服我自己了,居然把fill这个概念翻译完了 - -)
alright
你可能又会问,上哪儿找我的Gap呢
questions you would ask yourself about
where my gaps
这里很重要的一点要记住,你要尽可能少的去保存状态值
and the important thing to remember here
is to save as little state as possible
你要做的是把视图的信息给算出来
right you want to discover the
information about your view
第一个可视视图的位置和其偏移量都要算才行.
what's the first visible position what
is it offset don't try to track
不要想着设置状态值去追踪这些信息.
因为这通常会由于
that information because that typically
tends to lead to edge cases where you
你没有追踪到位都导致边界错误.
can track it correctly and then you
你会把事情推向另一个分支发展.所以正确的做法是
you are branching a statement all over the
place.ok use this as a
尽可能把fill这个函数当成一个无状态函数,
只借助内部状态找出
as stateless a function as you can
possibly do that discovers everything it
来找出我们所需的布局初始信息
needs up front
然后恰当的去运行布局过程.
and then runs the layout appropriately
on each pass
okay
顺便,我们这里举一个fill的例子
just by  way,an example,this is what a fill
fill函数应该就长得像这样
function might look like or you
might stop one out
这里,首先,你需要想出一些逻辑来找出so you know,at the beginning you're going to
have some logic to determine what the
第一个可视视图的位置,这个位置由于布局的不同
first visible position is depending on
your layout that
其位置的算法肯定也不相同.若是简单的算法,也许就像是
your could mean a number of things it's
probably just gonna be something simple
枚举所有的孩子视图,对其ViewHolder进行询问
like enumerating overall the child views
asking those Child's View holders what
其所处的位置是多少
their position are
要是你的列表是按线性布局的话,
那么所要找的位置就是其中最小的
and may be looking for the lowest value
OK that would be true for a linear want
如果是其他情形,那么就要依据
it may not be true depending on what your
布局的不同来选取不同的位置了.
总之,你要找出来第一个列表项的位置
your layout implementation is,but
figuring out what that first visible item is
如果需要的话,你还要把偏移量给找出来.
这就取决于你的列表有没有进行过转换
and if it's necessary what is its offset
is it has it been shifted
如果被转换过,我们就要对留白进行填充等等.
so that we need to of your fill a gap or
something like that
正如我之前所提到的
and then as i mentioned there are
RecyclerView中有一些帮助类的方法可供我们使用
a helper methods available on the
recycler view
这样方法可以帮助我们将视图传给回收器进行回收
to help you toss away of views so the
framework中几乎每个主要的方法都会传递给你两个对象
the two objects that you're going to see
passed to you in pretty much every major framework method
1是回收器的实例,2是叫做回收器状态的对象
is a recycler instance and something
called the recycler state
这两个对象一般都是绑定在一起工作的
and those two things all will work together
其工作目的是
在你需要做跟修改布局相关的事情时来帮你
for everything that you need to do
associated with modifying your layout so
我们这个例子中
in this case
recycler被传进入了API中的一个帮助方法
the recycler is passed to this helper
function which is part of the API
这个方法不用你来做实现,你只要告诉framework,
detachAndScrapAttachedViews就行了
that's not something you have to write
just detach and scrap attached views
这意思是说,把当前attached的视图全都
that says tossed every view that I has
currently attached to me
丢给Scrap堆.之后,
throw into scrap.OK,and then from there
你可以简单的遍历出你所需要的视图,
you can simply iterate through however
many views you need whether you have
不管你是要把这些视图布局到一个固定大小的窗口里,
还是你要用视图把整个界面的空间都布局满
like a fixed window size or you just
want to iterate through views until you
或者将这些视图应用到任何你想出来的布局算法中
run out of space whatever algorithm that you
want to use to do this
你都得把这些需要的视图给遍历出来.你要在
iterate through those views and get each one back
recycler中把每个视图给查找出来.
from the recycler so
getViewForPosition这个方法会告诉recycler,
我想在这个位置上进行布局
getViewForPosition will tell the recycler this is
the position I wanna lay out
接着recycler会返回给你所需要的视图,
并且已经给你绑定好了数据
and it will give you the view already
bound to the data that you need to do
这些数据会在你布局的时候被用到
that layout with
之后,就像你将视图布局到其他任何ViewGroup中一样,
你先要把视图给添加进入
OK and then just like you would in any
other view group you need add it
或者说是attach到父视图上,然后measure,layout
or attach it measure it and lay it out
这之后
oK then from there
最后一步是看看有没有剩下的视图
the final job is determining if there
are any views that were in my layout
这些在布局中没有被用到.之前,我们开始的时候,
我们是把当前所有的视图都丢给ScrapHeap
that I don't need anymore so when I went
through and I scrapped everything
如果在接下来的layout过程中,
仅仅使用到了我们所需的视图
if if the next step is to lay out just what I need
那么在Scrap中就有可能还剩下没被操作的视图
there may be views that were left in the scrap heap
这些视图就可能是滚出屏幕的视图,
也可能是由于某种原因
and those are views that I scrolled off screen or for whatever reason I don't
我不在需要的视图
need anymore
因为这些视图没有经过layout的过程
(因此就不会再出现在屏幕之上了)
because they didn't make it back into the layout pass.you can ask the recycler
此时你可以对recycler中的视图状态进行检查
view for its current list of what's in scrap
此时如果还有视图存在与Scrap中的话,我们是不需要的了
and if there is anything left in scrap at this stage I don't need it
那对于这些视图,我就可以把它们给回收了.
回收的过程就是
so I can recycle it.ok,so then this will just go through in
把视图从ScrapHeap中拿出来,
然后显式的将其它们丢给RecyclerPool
and take the views out at the scrap heap and explicitly put them in their cycle poor
这是一种更有效的回收视图的方式,来把你明确知道的
okay and that's a more efficient way of holding those views when you know
之后还会再绑定数据的视图进行回收.这并不意味着
that they're gonna need to be rebound to data later on,that doesn't mean that
你把这些剩下的存在于Scrap的视图给回收后,
if you run out of views and recycle
and the only views that are available are in scrap that
这些视图就不能进行数据绑定了.recycler不光从Scrap中,
也会从RecyclerPool中取出视图进行绑定.
it won't be able to rebind them.recycle will rebind data from scrap or recycle so it
你不必担心到底能不能
it's not something you necessarily have to worry about as to whether it will
让你的视图工作起来.这仅仅是一种优化操作
make your view work correctly.it's just an optimization
如果在recycler中正确的使用Scrap,
你就能对回收行为做最大的优化
if you use scrap in recycle appropriately
then you'll have the most optimized for recycling behavior
比方说内存管理或其他等等相关的.
in terms of memory management that sort of thing.okay
layout的过程讲完了.
okay
那么framework让我们这么干的好处在哪呢
其好处之一就是,在实现我的例子
so one of the advantages from the example that I
之前,我必须要对视图的索引进行处理
had put forth of doing this has to do with view indices
要实现这种布局,我第一个要考虑的问题就是
one of the first problem i doubt with when dealing with this,this fixed grid implementation
这不像是一个通常的线性单向滚动的
was unlike a traditional linear single scrolling
实现,这里在滚动时,视图的索引不是连续的
implementation the view indices aren't always consistent
在LinearLayout甚至GridLayout中,你都可以简单的
you know something like a LinearLayout or even a grid layout you can typically
依赖这样一个事实
rely on the fact that
列表中的第一个视图,就是第一个可见的视图
the first views in the list are the first visible
最后一个视图,就是最后一个可见的视图.你可以依赖于
and the last views in list is the last visible.and you can rely on a
视图的index和position以一种相对连续的方式进行映射
a fairly consistent mapping between view indices
当列表往上滚的时候,
and positions you know when you scroll up you would
你通常在列表前面插入视图,如果列表下滚
typically insert views at the front and
if as you scroll down you would
通常就在尾部进行添加.但是对于
append them to the end or vice versa but
that's not necessarily true with this
我们的例子来说这样做就不对了.
case you know in this case if the
如果用户正在查看网格中间的某些块元素
if the user is looking at some block of elements in the middle of the grid
视图的索引就可能看起来像这种样子,按照我布局的方式
the view indices might look something like this: based on the way I've laid them out
但是你可以看出来,如果你把左边和右边的
but you can kinda see that on the left and the right hand side there
视图索引当成适配器的位置来看时
those views are part of the range
从适配器的角度来看,它们就是不可见的
from the adapters perspective they just aren't visible right now
你可以想象的到,当我把这个窗口在视图上做各种平移时
so you can imagine that as i shift the window across these views
视图们就会以组的形式给添加进来.我可能
they will be brought in as groups
so I would bring in maybe
会添加4个视图来布局出下一列,
或者添加几个视图来布局下一行
for call 4 views in the next column
maybe a couple for the new row
这些视图以组的形式可能从各个方向上
(上,下,左,右)被添加进来
and it will come in groups that could be coming from all four sides
因此如果我要依赖任何
so if I want to rely on any sort
视图索引的连续性的话,我需要先把所有视图都丢掉,然后
of consistency in the view indices I need to toss everything away and
然后对其进行重新布局,来确保索引0的孩子总在左上方
relayout and that insures that child 0 is always at the top left
索引X的孩子总在右下方
child whatever is at the bottom right.ok
否则你就不能依赖索引连续性.
我并不是说你非得这么干.
otherwise I can't and I'm not saying you
have to rely on that but
但你如果非要为这么干找一个原因的话,
如果说你能够确定
but a little trick to help keep your sanity here is if you can be relatively sure
孩子视图的索引
that the child indices are in the right
一直是正常的话,这会帮你简化你一些检查的逻辑
order all the time then it it helps simplify some of that inspection logic
这种检查是当你对视图做改变时有可能需要做的,等等
that you may need to do later on for changes and stuff like that
因此,这里说的
仅仅是遵从framework进行layout的一个好处
so just an advantage of using that implementation
取决于你自定义布局的功能性和你对fill方法的改写
and this depending on your functionality and how you mutate that fill method I showed you
你可以通过手动调用attach和detach
you can use attach and detach manually
来对屏幕上的视图进行重新排序.
如果你不准备将他们都丢给Scrap的话
to reorder these views so you know if
you're not necessarily scrapping them
但是,出于某种原因,你仅仅是想将视图进行重新排序的话
but for whatever reason you just want to
reorder them so that the same views have
视图还是同样的视图,但是视图的索引却被重新排序的话
different indices that are in this order
你要先把视图全detach掉,
然后将视图以正确的顺序给attach回来
detach them all and reattach them in the right order that will
这样才能使孩子视图有合适的视图索引
that will give them the proper view index from a child perspective inside of the parent view
好了,咱接下来要讲一下
okay so let's talk a little bit about
整个布局过程的步骤了.
假设你现在已经写好了一个fill方法
the steps to build one of these things,so assuming that you have a proper method put together
将我传授给你的秘诀都用上了.
one that sort of follows that recipe that I showed you.
现在,我就传授你如何将前面讲过的东西串联在一起.
this is sort of how we would put these things in place,so the first
我把使用recycler对视图进行布局的第一级别称为
the first level that I call it of working recycler view layout
让布局管理器能工作起来.布局管理器有很多回调方法
is just to get the thing working,right.so that there's a handful call back
需要你来进行重写和实现
来使一个实际的布局管理器可以工作起来
you need to to override and implement just to get an actual layout manager functioning
第一个要重写的方法就是onLayoutChildren,
这是一个初始化的方法
the first one is on layout children this is the initial method
这个方法会由framework调用,当任何一个特定的布局改变
they will be called by the framework anytime a significant layout change
发生在RecyclerView身上时
happens to the recycler view
RecyclerView就会把这个改变委托给布局管理器
the recycler view will delegate to the manager that
告诉它,需要它通过onLayoutChildren进行一次新的布局,
注意,onLayoutChildren并不会被重复调用
it needs to do a new layout through onLayoutChildren.this is not called repeatedly
所以,其不会在每次布局改变时都被调用,而仅在初始化时
meaning it's not called on every change
but it'll be called for initial layout
还有当RecyclerView的大小被改变时也会调用
it will be called if the size of the recycler view changes if you ever call
如果你有调用过RecyclerView.requestLayout的话,
就会触发onLayoutChildren被调用
requestLayout on the recycler view this is what you're gonna see
如果写的fill方法合格的话,在onLayoutChildren中,
你要干的全部工作
and again if you haven't inappropriately written fill method all you have to do
仅仅是运行fill而已.不管你在RecyclerView中
是否已经存在了视图,或者其中视图为空
in here is to run it.whether you have views in there already or whether it's empty
这都没关系,你仅仅在里面运行fill即可,就能把事情全搞定
doesn't matter you just run your fill inside of here and be done
但是,我们还在这个方法中添加一些对用户操作的控制
okay,but we want to add a little bit of user act in there interactivity to this function as well
所以,你必须在RecyclerView中来决定或者说是通知framework
so you have to determine or you have to report back to the framework in recycler view
这个视图能在哪个坐标轴上进行滚动,是垂直轴呢?
which axis can this view scrolling,can it scroll vertically
还是水平轴?或者在我的例子中,两者都行
can scroll horizontally or in my case,both
多数情况下,你仅仅需要在这两个方法中
so in most of these cases you would only return true
的一个里面返回true就行了.
但是我们的固定网格实现两个方法中都返回了true
from one of these methods but the fix grid implementation returns it for
这样它就能在水平方向和垂直方向同时滚动了.
both so that it can scroll both horizontally and vertically at the same time
如果你没有从这两个方法中返回true
if you don't return true from these methods then
那么RecyclerView的内部实现就简单地
不把这个方向上事件分发给自己来处理
the recycler view implementation simply won't delivery events back to you
因为它知道你只会在一个方向上滚动,因此会锁定滚动
knowing that you're scrolling in one direction,the other basically locks scrolling
在另一个方向上
in that particular orientation but
而真正实现视图滚动的处理逻辑是在
the actual implementation of this scrolling functionality happens in the
scrollXBy方法中,水平方向滚动的话就是scrollHorizontallyBy,
垂直的话就是scrollVerticallyBy
scroll x by methods so scroll horizontally or vertically by
这俩方法会重复地被调用,这跟你在
these methods will be called repeatedly very similar to the scroll by methods you
View里或ViewGroup里看到的scrollBy方法是非常相似的,
would see on a view or view group
当用户的手势交互到来时.因此这是布局管理器的责任
as user interaction is coming in.so it is the responsibility
去处理视图的移动
of the layout manager to handle moving the views
RecyclerView本身是不处理视图滚动的,
它仅仅预先把信息提供给布局管理器
recycle view doesn't do that for you
okay it just gives you the information
以使其自身可以被滚动
up front to be able to do that
因此这些方法在调用的时候会附带着
framework根据用户的输入计算出来的信息
so these methods will be called with the information that the framework has determined from the user input
从根本上来讲,这两个方法会循序渐进地被调用,
每次被调用都会传递给你一个delta值
basically they'll give you a delta value and this is called incrementally
这个值代表着framework所认为的,此时,
你应当将你的视图平移多远
of how far the framework thinks you should shift your views
当然,这得分横向平移和纵向平移
and of course in which direction horizontally or vertically,ok
接下来,这就需要你来对视图进行真正
and then it will be up to you to actually do
的移动了,同时,你还要对移动过程中的边界条件做处理
the movement as well as making any determinations about boundary conditions
布局管理器有义务去告诉framework,当视图滚到
right?the layout managers responsible for telling the framework when you hit the
内容的结尾处时,应该停止滚动
end of the content and you need to stop scrolling
在此当前方向.其实通知framework的报告就放在return值里
in that particular direction.oK now that report is actually done in the terms the return value
从这个函数中返回的任何值
so when whatever value you return from this function
都标明给framework,此时你实际上移动了多远的距离
designates to the framework how far you actually traveled
接着,framework会根据其被告知移动的距离来对视图进行移动
and then the framework will make determination based on how much how far
(同上)
I told you to travel
如果返回值为0,那么framework就会假定视图滚动到了边界
if there's a difference there it assumes it hit boundary and it's going to do
framework就会为你做一些事情,比方说会帮你画边缘发光的效果
things for you like drawing edge glows
还有像其他的边缘效果,你肯定不想看到你的布局管理器
and other edge effect behavior that you probably don't wanna see if you're not
没有这种边缘效果,
因此你必须要对return值是如何来的十分关心
all the way at the end,so you have to be very careful about how that return value
(同上)
actually comes up
这就是scrollXby方法的示例
so this is kind of an example
这是一段在FiexedGrid中的代码片段
of what you might see.this is a snippet version of what's in fixed grid for scroll horizontally
首先你被传入一个称为dx的值
so you're given a value that they call in this case dx
这个值就是framework认为的你应当滚动的值.首先,
thats how far they think you should scroll.first thing you have to determine
你可能要根据此次滚动发生的方向来决定
perhaps based on which direction that scrolling occurs is.
我能否滚动这么远,我有没有碰到边界
can I scroll that far or have I hit boundary
最后才来决定实际要平移的距离.这里有个好处是,
and determine how far you're actually going to shift.now the nice thing is
你不必对孩子视图们进行迭代,然后对其进行单独的移动
you don't have to iterate over the child views and individually move them
RecyclerView的LayoutManager
为我们提供水平和垂直平移的帮助方法
recycler view layout manager provides of these offset children methods both horizontal and vertical
来帮我们对当前attached的所有视图进行平移转换
that will do the the work of shifting all views that are currently attached
因此,你只需要计算好偏移量就行了
so all you have to determine is the actual difference
然后把这个偏移量传递给帮助方法即可.不过,由于RecyclerView
and then just passed that into the method but because recycler view doesn't
对其孩子视图的布局是一无所知的,
really know how your layout looks
一旦当前attach的视图被移动了,就可能生成Gap,因此这就需要
once the views have been moved you may have created a gap so it's up to you
那么处理gap方法是?再运行一次现成的fill方法即可.
在我的例子里
to go back and run another fill(),oK now in my implementation and you can look at the details
(你可以去github看),我的实现实际上为fill提供了
in the example on github.but in my implementation I actually provided
额外的direction参数,以此来辅助
direction keyword back to the fill,just to help sort of assist when I needed to shift my
我对positions的前移或后移,
到底是前移还是后移这要看当前视图的滚动状态
my positions backwards or forward based on which way this scrolling was going on
这里的direction并不是我所描述的fill技巧所必需的,
that's not really required in the technique that I'm describing it just
这仅仅是方便我的视图二维滚动而已
it was helpful for my bidirectional scrolling
你也可以根据你的fill算法,来传入你所需的额外参数
but it it's not really part of,its whatever your algorithm needs
以便你能让你的算法效率最高
you know to be able to do that in the most efficient way
这里的返回值
okay and then as I mention the return value their
必须是你实际滚动值的负值
has to be the difference of what was actually scrolled
如果你直接返回dx,那么视图的滚动就不会被停止
if you just take this and you just return dx you'll never end up scrolling
而如果你老是返回0,那么任何时候你尝试去滚动时,
视图都不会被滚动
and if you always return 0 never scroll at all anytime you try to scroll you'll
你会老是看到边缘被拉起而产生的发光效果
just get infinity edge glows all the time
因此,你必须得详细的在代码中体现出你何时能移动,何时不能
okay so you have to be very specific about when you can and when you can't move
这取决于你是否滚动到了你的列表内容的边界
based on whether or not you've hit a boundary of your content
在最低程度上,
at a minimum
这就行了.这些就是你要干的全部事情了,
这些能保证你获取到一个能工作得起来的
that's it.that's all you really need to implement to get a working
布局管理器了.它能帮你把视图布局出来,
还能让你对视图进行移动
layout managers something that will lay views out you can move them around
从用户交互的视角来看,所有你能期望得到的,它都能帮你满足
you know all the things you would expect from user interaction perspective
尽管我们还有一些额外的特性可以加进来,
这些特性也是之后我们应该加的
other additional features you can add and probably should add
但是,我刚讲的是基础.就算你只做到最低程度,那么你起码可以
overtime but thats sort of the basics,like even get that far you can at least
来检验出你的算法是否能工作以及你的布局功能是否管用等等
determine if your algorithm works and your layout functionalities are okay and all that sort of thing I
干完基本的事情之后呢,如果你还有额外的时间的话
the next step if you have additional time is
通常地,我们还需要让布局管理器能对数据集变化做响应
typically to start reacting to dataset changes
实际上,这里我们的工作量并没有很多,
大多数的工作framework都内置实现了
there're really not a whole lot of work to do here.most of it is built right in but
但是有个一方法叫做onAdapterChanged
there is one additional method here called on adapter changed
你可以在里面做一些优化的工作
that you can provide some optimizations inside of
其实你不必非要重写这个方法,但是重写会有更多的益处.
这方法被触发时机是
you don't have to override this but it can be helpful.this will be triggered
当RecyclerView被提供一个完全不同的Adapter的时候
if the recycler view ever is provided with a completely different
因此,当某人再次调用setAdapter且传入的数据集不同时,
adapter instance so if they call said adapter again with some
onAdapterChanged就会在LayoutManager里面被调用
other object,then this will be called in the layout manager
此时,你就可以利用这个调用,来进行一些优化操作
and you can use that as an optimization opportunity
做法很简单,就是把当前的视图全清空.
要注意,我并不是把视图丢给recycler
to simply clear all the views,now notice I'm not tossing them to the recycler
而是想把视图给全部移除掉.这样做是根据下面的假设
I just want them removed completely.the assumption here is that
如果设置了一个完全不同的adapter,
那么我们的数据集肯定也完全不同了
if we're getting a completely new adapter it's definitely new data
还有视图类型也可能会是新的,因此这里并不需要
and it's probably gonna be new view types as well,so there's no need
我来把所有视图都丢给recycler,因为就算丢给recycler,
for me to dump everything I have into the recycler,coz this just going to end up
它之后也会将这个视图给进行清空的
having a toss those away later anyway
并不是说如果不干这件事,就会引起崩溃.
而是说我们可以在这儿做优化
it's not that we would break if it did that but we can optimize that out
一旦发现adapter有改变,就把所有视图给移除
by saying if the adapter changes,just remove everything
注:(humorous) A phrase telling someone to pursue a path directly without deviations."
不用再传给recycler了,这样就会显得太死搬硬套了
by pass the recycler,don't collect two hundred dollars.
我们都知道在Adapter中的notifyDataSetChanged方法
now we all know notify dataset change on an adapter,right
如果adapter中的数据改变了,我们就出发这个方法来更新界面
if something has changed in the data we trigger this method to update the view
在ListView中是这么干的,在RecyclerView也仍然存在
right it was that way in listview still exists in recycler view
如果是做一个基础的实现的话,你并不需要干其他工作
at a base implementation you don't have to do anything different here
RecyclerView中的notifyDatasetChanged
仅会触发一个新的布局改变
notify dataset change just triggers a new layout change
此时,再一次,如果你的fill方法写得好的话,
你就啥也不用干,等着布局管理器帮你重新布局即可
and if your fill again is set up appropriately you just relayout
依赖这种实现方式,你可能唯一想干的事儿是
right the only thing you might want to persist in this sort of implementation dependent is
对于adapter的改变,你可能想让第一个可见视图的position持续存在
for an adapter change you might wanna persist with the current first position was
因此在你运行fill之前,你可能需要先找到这个位置.不过,再一次,
so you may want to discover that before you run your fill.but again depending on
取决于你对fill的实现,你可能在fill里面已做过找位置这事了
how you've written your fill you're probably already doing that anyway
因此,布局管理器兴许就能尝试着对新数据进行布局
且其开始布局的位置会跟之前一样
so they can attempt with the new data to lay out from the same first visible position
但是,如果你有视图被丢弃过的话,或其他类似的事情有发生的话,
okay but if you toss those away already or something like that
那么你可能就需要对这个位置值做追踪
you may want to track that value
直到新的布局开始或类似的事情发生即可
just very briefly until the new layout comes around or something like that
否则的话,你就要从初始位置开始布局了,布局管理器仍然可以工作
otherwise you could just lay it out from the beginning,it would still work
有一点需要你在意的是,如果你的adapter设置成了固定id的话
the one caveat to this is that if your adapter has stable ids
RecyclerView就假定你在此时是有足够的数据
recycler view assumes at that point that it actually has enough data to
来对布局变化尝试着进行动画
try and animate the change
因此调用notifyDatasetChanged会触发新的动画序列
and so calling notify dataset changed will trigger an animation sequence
一会咱们就要谈到animations啦,
但是如果你的adapter没有固定id的话
and we'll talk about animations a little bit later but if you if your adapter doesn't do that
那仅仅就是进行一次一般的布局而已.以此来适应新的数据集
this will just be a snap layout.it'll adjust to the new data
alright
如果前边的活干完后,咱手头里恰好还留有点时间的话
well let's say that we happen to have a little bit more extra time on our hands
咱还想要搞点别的的东西放入到布局管理器中
we want to get a little bit more fancy with this functionality
那么,接下来我们能加入到manager中的特性就是
让RecyclerView可随意滚动到目标位置
the next feature that we could add to our manager is target scrolling
像这种外部的APIs
so the external APIs for allowing
这种可以让开发者对视图进行滚动到指定位置的APIs
其滚动形式不管是立即式的
a developer to scroll your layout to a specific position whether that immediately
还是以某种动画过渡的,这些framework里都没有,
这就需要你来提供
or in some animated fashion again are not baked and you have to provide some
一些实现,来告诉framework该如何去做
implementation of how that works
因此,对于这种非动画的scrollToPosition方法的实现
so for the scroll to position case which is a non animated case
这种实现可以非常简单.就像我之前提到过的
it can be pretty simple just like in the case I mentioned before
你需要以某种方式追踪到当前被请求的位置是哪个
you would need to track somehow what the requested position was
接下来很简单,调用一下requestLayout即可.
这会触发一次新的布局
and then just call request layout that will trigger a new layout which will
从而触发可以能做fill操作的onLayoutChildren方法
trigger on layout children which you can just do fill
从这儿你总该看出来了吧,如果你的fill写的好
right.so,you can start to see how if you do your
那么你干任何事都能用到它.你就不必去做很多
fill right it becomes everything to you and you don't have to do a whole
其他的琐碎事情来修饰好RecyclerView啦
lot else to sort of decorate around
为了取得更炫酷的效果,
我们有这种smoothScrollToPosition方法
oK,to get a little bit more fancy,we have the smooth scroll to position
作为一个开发者,我们会想着让视图
and this is where we would want as a developer we would want the view to
已动画的形式移动到目标位置.
actually animate into place.oK now the
而实现这种功能需要去实现一个
the functionality for doing this requires an implementation of something
被叫做SmoothScroller的帮助类.这个是个由
called a smooth scroller.this is an abstract class provided by the
framework提供的抽象类.你可以重写和新建你自己的实现
by the framework that you can override and create your own implementation
(下)当Scroller对你的视图进行动画和寻找目标位置时,
of essentially what should happen on an incremental basis
(上)来自定义对dx,dy这种增量进行处理
as it animates around your view trying to find the target
这种接口其实还是有点复杂的
oK this interface is actually fairly complex there's
我记得不太清了,
你可能需要重写5到10个方法才能让其工作起来
I can't remember five to 10 methods that you have to override to make that happen
你当然可以老老实实地这么做
you can certainly do that if you're not a
如果你对framework给出的行为感到不爽的话
if you're not happy with the behavior that the framework gives you
不过这儿的确还存在着一种被称为
LinearSmoothScroller的实现
but there is an implementation called linear smooth scroller that is provided
其存在于support.v7中,你可以拿来做代替.
这个类帮我做了大多数的工作
in the support package that you can just take instead.this does most of the work for you
通过提供一种线性的补间动画
by providing a linearly interpolated animation
运行在其往各种目标位置进行移动的路上.
on its way to whatever the target position is and the only piece of
这里你要提供的唯一信息就是
information you have to provide in this case
以坐标系的眼光来看,我们的目标位置在哪.
is where is the target position and that's from a coordinate's perspective
当这个被称为smoothScrollToPosition的方法被调用时
so when this method is called smooth scroll to position you basically
你得搞清楚你现在第一个可视视图的位置是在哪
have to figure out what's the first visible position I have now
还要知道你的目标位置在哪,
这样你就能算出进行移动的向量了
what's the target that they're trying to get to and then this computation what they call a vector
向量包含了你到达目标位置的方向
on what is the direction that I need to scroll to get there
不管这个方向可能是上,下,左,右,斜,其都必须是个一维的向量
is it left?is it right?is it up?is it down,is it diagonal?but has to be some linear value
通常,由于布局的多种多样的,
因此你得搞清楚这两个位置之间的真实距离
ok and so you would typically figure out what's the conceptual distance between the two
你可以把你能想到的都放在一起来考虑
based on you know whatever guess you can put together
在我的例子里,所有的孩子视图的大小都是固定的,
所以我会有一个很准确的猜测
in my case all the views are the same size,so I can have a really good guess
因为我清楚地知道我需要移动多远
because I knew exactly how far i would need to travel
但这并不是必须的.
Scroller并不需要知道要进行移动的精确距离
but that may not necessarily be the case.it doesn't have to be the exact distance
它只需要知道要移动的方向即可
it just has to know the direction
一旦知道了方向和位置,LinearSmoothScroller能开始工作了
and then linear smooth scroller is gonna go through and run an incremental fashion
它会不断地在目的方向上执行动画滚动
they're gonna walk through they're just going to incrementally animate
直到到达目标位置为止
and scroll in whatever direction it needs to get to that position
它的机制就是每滚动出一个新位置上的视图,
就去检查目标位置的视图是否被布局出来
and it'll scroll can see if it's been laid out scroll again
它会滚动,检查,再滚动,再检查
see if it's been laid out its just gonna hunt and hunt until
直到其感兴趣的位置被layout出来为止.
the position that it's interested in has finally come into the layout.it was just
这个过程会调用你写过的那些scroll方法
going to be triggering your scroll methods that you've already written
直到其找到了目标值,它才会停止滚动
and as soon as it finds that value then it will stop scrolling
直到目标视图在屏幕上完全可见,
once that fully visible on the display at that point then it will just
它才会结束工作.因此,你可以重写SmoothScroller
it'll end.oK so you can override the smooth scroller
然后传给它目标位置,最后只需调用一下startSmoothScroll
set the target position and to just start it and that's really the simplest end
你就完成了最基本的动画滚动视图的实现
of the implementation to animated scrolling
最后一部分,如果你的时间很充裕的话
the last piece if you have a lot extra
time
或者你觉得某些地方还不太满意的话.你可以尝试
and maybe some sanity left you can attempt
去添加一些动画支持.目前,
to add some animation support now out of the box
尽管RecyclerView的确支持被称为
defaultItemAnimations的东西
recycler view does support what they called default item animations
利用RecyclerView的新特性,在它上面实现动效不像
what the new features of recycler view that was not easy to
在ListView上那么难,这种新特性就是
implement on something like listview was
不管你对列表项是做插入还是移除或者是做一些视图改变
if you inserted a new item or removed it or made some changes
都可以以一种很美妙的方式来针对这些操作定制动画
animating all that in a nice fancy way for the user
像framework里的核心布局管理器类(LLM,GLM,SGLM等)
the functionality with all the core layout managers
其作用是提供一种很基础的算法来支持ItemAnimator
is to provide a very basic algorithm for that out of the box
我一会儿会向你展示核心布局管理器的动画,
但我要先给大家讲下其原理
and I have an animation to show you what that looks like but essentially
布局管理器会对视图进行监测
it just looks at the views
它会观察列表项被操作前后的变化,然后尝试根据
looks at the change before and after and then tries to determine based on
前后布局的快照来决定
this layout and this layout in the two snapshots
哪些视图不见了,哪些视图是新增的,
以及哪些视图是被移动过了的
what views have gone away,what views are new and what views are moved around
它就会把老的视图给淡出,新的视图给淡入以及
and it will fade out the old views,fade in the new views and
对其他还在屏幕上的视图进行平移
simply translate the other ones on screen okay
在大多数情况下,这种实现工作的非常好.
但是你会发现
and in a lot cases it does a pretty good job but you'll see there are some
当你在做自定义布局管理器时,
采用了这种免费的动画的话,这儿会存在一些问题
problems with what you get for free if you're doing a custom layout because you
你可能想要把某些视图给移出屏幕,
因为这些视图不属于当前位置了
may be animating views off screen that because they're no longer there the default
默认的动画实现就会认为这些视图已经消失了
animation just thinks they've disappeared
因此会把这些视图给淡出掉而不是优雅地将它们移动到
so it fades them out instead of gracefully moving them
其在概念上来讲,应该所处的位置上
to where they conceptually were supposed to go
接下来,哥就教你如何让布局管理器来支持这种优雅的动画
ok.and so we'll take a look at what you need to do to sort of provide that
这在android里面其实被称为predictive列表项动画
如果你想要
so android calls that predictive item animations and if you want to support
在你的布局管理器中支持它的话
that in your layout manager
那么你只需要告诉布局管理器即可.
在supportsPredictiveItemAnimations中返回true即可
you just have to tell them.to say yes I support predictive animations return true from this method
这样做会稍微改变一下你布局管理器的布局行为
and this will change your layout behavior just a little bit
这种情况下,每当有列表项改变时,都将成为一个触发点
in this case anytime an item change is triggered
现在,我们的初始化布局还是跟从前一样
now for an initial layout or anything like that still gonna be the same
但是当你移除或者添加列表项等等类似的操作时
but you remove an item or you insert an item something like that
在这个item仍是可见的时候
and that item is visible at the moment
那么,实际上,布局的过程就变成两条通路
then the layout process actually becomes a two pass layout
它会在被称为preLayout的状态下,
首先调用onLayoutChildren
it calls on layout children first in what they called the pre layout state
这个状态下,
布局管理器中的所有视图和适配器中的所有数据
this is a state where all the views all the data from the adapter
都被处理成
is massaged such that it looks the way it would have looked
item变化前的状态.
因此,这儿为你提供了一个机会来执行一次layout pass
before the change this gives you an opportunity to run a layout pass
这个layout pass就被称为
对布局前的视图快照的preLayout
in what they call the pre layout of the the initial snapshot
以屏幕上的视图的观点来看,这意味着
oK,so from the views on screen perspective this means you just
你只需要运行一次你fill方法即可,但是你可能还需要
run your traditional fill but you might need to
对被移除屏幕的视图做记录,因为如果有视图被移除屏幕
make note if any of the views that were on screen were removed
你就需要对gap进行填充,
如果此时你让默认的动画来干活的话
you've got gaps to fill and if you just let the default animations do their work
在gap出现的时候,它们就开始执行动画了,
它们就仅仅把新的视图给淡入进来
they will animate until they can see that gap and they'll just fade the new view in
但是,如果你想要达到那种视图滑入槽位的效果的话
but if you wanna make it look like the view actually slides into place
那么你就要在这个layout pass里,
把槽位上的视图给布局出来
you have to lay it out during this pass
你需要将视图布局在屏幕里其应当进入的位置之上
and you lay it out in the location of screen where it should come from
因此,这些视图称之为appearing视图
ok.so those are what they call appearing views
这些在LayoutParams中为你提供了额外的信息
and they give you additional information on the layout parameters which you can
LayoutParams可以用ViewHolder中获取
get from the view holder
对于每个单独的视图,不管这个视图此时是否真的可见
for each individual view as to whether or not this view that you can see
只要你在LayoutParams.isViewRemoved为真的话,
在下一次布局时,这个视图就一定会消失掉
has actually been removed and in the next step it's gone and if that's the case
你可能发现此时你有2到3个视图要被移除掉了,
那么你就要保证
you say wow I've got maybe two or three views that were removed I need to make sure
你能从别处拿来2到3个appearing视图给添加进来
I add two or three appearing views in wherever they should be so that the
这样以来,
animation才会把这些视图以正确的动画形式给带进来
animation brings them in the way they're supposed to look
所以,你该把要被移除的视图给记录下来,
以便于你的appearing视图来进行利用
okay,so you want to take note of how many are removed so that you can use that for the appearing views
在这里,你通常还会做另一件事
the other thing that you would typically do during this step
注:take stock v. 盘货; 清查存货;
对在当前布局里的视图进行盘查
is take some stock of what's currently in the layout
为的是在你操作了item之后,你有没有视图
so that after the fact you can determine if any are the views
虽没有被显式的被移除,但其此时已不在当前布局中了
that weren't explicitly removed are no longer in the layout
因为这些视图是被滚出了屏幕.
because they shifted off screen
如果是这种情况的话,你就要在布局的第二个阶段
and if that's the case you need to lay them out during the second phase
也就是我们通常进行布局的阶段,
把这些视图布局在那些被滚出屏幕的位置之上
which is the the regular layout phase in their off screen positions.ok
因此,在preLayout过程里,你要对appearing视图进行布局
so during pre layout you have to lay out those appearing views
然后把此时的布局快照里面视图的状态给记录下来
and just take note of what the state of that snapshot is
最后,你再来运行一次平常的fill即可
and then run your fill the way you normally would
之后,onLayoutChildren还会被再调用一次
then that method is gonna be called again in this case that
此时,isPreLayout会返回false.
那么我们的布局过程就跟运行一次fill没啥不同了.
is pre layout is gonna be set to false and this is no different than any other fill
现在,适配器中的位置和数据都被设置成
now all the adapter positions and all the values are set the way they are
变化后的值了.此时你就该把变化后的东西全布局出来了
after the change and you can lay everything out
你就差这最后一步没有走了
and then you just have that final step
你是要对布局管理器说,现在我不需要adapter里的这部分了
of saying ok,at this point I don't need this piece in ...(adapter)
这部分已经不在了,我需要把这些视图给布局出屏幕,
this piece has gone away I need to lay it out off screen
这样视图的动画才能按正确的方向滑入.
so that the animation can slide in the right direction
ok
让我们快速的浏览一个例子,来领会其中的奥妙
let's take a look at a quick example here you can get an idea there so
现在你的onLayoutChildren方法看起来就变得有点复杂了
now you're on layout children might look a little bit more complicated right
在preLayout时,你需要对LayoutParams中的信息
so during pre layout is where you're going to make that information
进行检查,来得到实际上被移除去的视图
check that information about how many views were actually removed
如果有视图被移除,我就得在这个位置上
were there any,if there was a view removed then I need to account for that
加入一点appearing的逻辑了
by adding some appearing logic so
在我的例子中,我把这事放在fill方法里面了
in in my implementation if you look at the example I added that to the sill
因此会把任何需要加进布局的appearing视图传给fill
so the fill he's also passed if there are any additional appearing view that needs to add
在fill里对这些视图进行另外的布局,以使其将来会被看到
and it lays those out in addition to what would (otherwise) be able to see
好吧,我刚说的就是fill中比较隐晦的地方了.与这类似的
okay so that's kind of hidden in here and similarly
我们可以在preLayout之后,也就是我们
we can look after pre layout after we've
真正完成fill方法之后,我们可以对Scrap表进行检查
done our fill for real and we can check that scrap list again and say
是否Scrap中还有剩余的视图
was there anything that was left in scrap
如果还有的话,这些视图其实就是disappearing视图,
它们没有被移除掉(只是不在当前屏幕上显示而已)
if there was then those are actually disappearing views,they weren't removed
因此,对这些视图,我们也要对其再进行一次布局
or and they...you anything like that so we
lay them out again
你可以再运行一次fill.但是更简单的是你可以抽象出
so you you could run a fill what's usually easier is just too abstract that
这种布局逻辑,封装成函数,传入特定的视图再次调用即可
layout logic and call it again for that specific view
同时,你得明白,这个操作是针对移出屏幕的视图进行的
and figure out this is where the view should be off screen
现在,我会快速地向你展示这里的不同之处.
alright,so just quickly,i will show you what that difference looks like
如果将defaultItemAnimation应用到我的例子里的话
ok,so with default item animations on the example that I had
达到的效果就是你现在所见到的,你能清楚的知道这并不符合
this is kind of what you get and you can you can see how it's not exactly what we
我们所期望的优雅动画的要求.这儿的红色视图
were looking for. so in this case the red view
是我们将要移除的视图,绿色视图是
is the one we're going to remove and the green views are the ones that should
将要进行位置转换的视图,但它们的做法并不符合我们的想法
shift location but they don't quite do what they're supposed to
当我们移除掉这个红色的视图时,这儿所发生的事情就是
right so when we remove this view what happens is that
所有在左边的视图也都淡出了
all the views on the left also fade out
然后它们会在其新位置上淡入
and then they fade in in their new locations
这就是因为RecyclerView对视图的动画形式是一无所知的
and that's because the recycler view doesn't know any better
它只知道在preLayout之后,这些视图就不在原来位置上了
it just knows that after pre layout they weren't there anymore
当我对视图滚动时,
我能看到这些视图实际上还存在于RecyclerView中
and then when I scroll over to see where they actually are
它们会在新的layout中出现.如何来修正这个问题呢,
我们要通过添加对predictive动画支持的属性
they'll show up there in the new layout.ok by adding proper predictive animation support
这样我才能修改其默认的动画行为,
在我的例子中也是通过这种方法来实现的
I can modify that behavior and again this is the way the example actually works if you go run it
我可以改变其行为,这样以来,这些绿的视图就会
I can modify their behaviors so that those green views
沿着既定的方向滑出屏幕到其应该所处的位置上
slide off screen to where they're supposed to go into that direction.
在用户的屏幕上,我们可能只能看到这些视图
now from the user screen they'll probably just slide
移出屏幕而已,除非你有足够大的显示屏能容纳下所有视图
off screen unless there is a large enough display for them might see the whole thing
在我们这个例子中
but in that case they actually
我们这么做的好处在于我们能让用户看到视图是如何移走的
that you get the benefit of the user seeing where they should go
因此,当用户要去滚动查找这些视图时,
会发现视图的确是在那里的
so that when they scroll over they're actually there,right.it's that idea of
这可谓把通过用动画引导用户操作的思想给运用得淋漓尽致了
teaching the user how things are supposed to go by animating them to the proper locations
如果对这些视图采用淡出动画的话,
用户就可能认为这些视图被移除了,而实际上并没有
if they just all fade out,they might think they remove them all which is not correct
因此,这就是实现predictiveItemAnimation的背后思想
ok.so that's the idea behind implementing predictive item animations to give you some better info
okay so
我再给大家提供一点关于RecyclerView Layout的相关信息
just a couple more pieces of information to wrap up here so
我们刚谈论到的例子在我的github页面上
the example that I've been discussing here I is on my github page
我的那个应用里面还有一些其他的关于FGLM的基本用例
that application also has a few other basic samples in it for using the grid
以及等等类似的东西,不过你放心,里面有着完整的
layout managers and things like that but it has the full source code for that fixed
FGLM实现的源码.你可以研究其中所有
grid implementations you can dive into all the
你感兴趣的地方.同时,我还写了一系列相当
(hairy) details if you're interested.I also went through a series a fairly
详细的博客,在我构建这个布局管理器的时候
detailed blog posts as I was building that thing
所以,如果你对我在做这个东西的时候抓掉了多少头发感兴趣的话
so if you wanna get a sense for how much hair i actually tore out while doing this
你可以把我的博客也过一遍
you can go through and read that
具体来讲,如果你要做的布局管理器跟我这种相类似的话
specifically if you're doing anything similar to what I did with that
都是这种间断区间的grid,你在屏幕上所看到的
that sort of disconnected range where the grid and what you're seeing
仅仅是整体布局的一个子集,以及这些视图的位置
is actually just a subset of the overall layout but the views that are in between
处于是区间中间
are actually in the middle of the range
如果是这种非线性的一维的布局的话
which you wouldn't typically have with the linear
那么你可能就需要去读一读我系列里的最后一篇文章了
you might want to read the last blog post
我称这篇文章为Redux篇,我在其中讨论的一些
that I call the redux where I actually discuss some other bugs and
Layout Manager API的bugs,
这些bug为这种布局管理器的实现又增加了难度
issues with the layout manager API that actually makes that implementation much more difficult than it should be
以及其他一些为解决bug而要求你所做的事情.
and some other things you have to do to work around that.
不过,如果你是在做一种更简单的实现的话
if you're doing a much more simpler implementation
如果其只是在一个坐标轴上布局的话,
那就不存在这种间断的问题了
that's either single axis doesn't have that disconnection problem
你可能不会遇到这种问题,但是读读文章还是会很有收益的
then you won't have any issues like that but it might be an interesting read
除此之外呢,SDK的文档也是写的很好的,
and then the SDK also has some pretty good documentation on just getting you
能使你快速上手RecyclerView
started with recycler view there.
okay
我看了下时间,我不知道我们是否会有
so looking at the time I don't know do we have
时间来留给大家提问.
any time for questions
噢,有一点时间空余.因此现在我接受一些问题的提问,
等时间到了,如果还有更多问题的话,我们台下解决.
couple,okay.we will take a couple questions and then if there anymore we'll kind of walk out stage.
好,那位我最先看到
I saw him first up
你所说的并不影响Decorators
what you mean by they don't affect the decorators
正确
that's correct
取决于你如何实现你的Decoratorsthe the information,depending on how you implement the actual decorator
如果你在Decorator里采用孩子的高度或宽度这些信息
if you're using that information of basically what's the height or the width
来给孩子视图画装饰的时候
of the child to know where to draw those lines
这些信息并不会随时更新
that information is not updated incrementally
其只会在初始化的时候进行更新
so it's only gonna be updated when its in its initial state
在列表被操作改变后,它需要给你提供一份新的信息
and then after the change it should give you the new information so
你可能会看到它跳到其合适的位置去,
但是它不会向你说的那样平移转换
you might see it jump into where its proper position is but it won't transition like that
因为那个信息不会...
because that information is not...
如果我在那个视图上调用getDecoratedHeight的话
if I called again get decorated height on that view
这个值并不会被改变
on each of those instances it's not going to change until the
直到其处在一个新的状态
the value is actually in its new state,cos from that perspective
height本身不是逐渐变化的变量,它只有一个初始状态
the height itself is not incremental it has its initial state and its final
和结束状态,这里唯一改变的就是drawing.
state the only thing that changes is the drawing
因此,你必须通过某种方式去监听到那个事件
so you have to you have to somehow listen for that event
然后试着手动触发它,虽然你可以这么干
and try to trigger it manually which you can do I
但是布局管理器本身
就提供了这些像列表项插入,删除等等之类的方法
the layout manager does have a handful of methods for on item removed added inserted that sort of thing
这些方法能通知到你有事件发生
that can signal you when that event is occurring
因此把你的动画匹配的相应的事件上去
so that you can try to match it as best as you can with your animation
除此之外,并没有其他办法来直接给你操作反馈在decorator中
but otherwise that yeah, unfortunately it doesn't give you that feedback directly in the decorator
yes
刚开始的时候,你讲到布局管理器中去存储很多状态是不好的
layout manager very beginning you said that keeping a lot of state is bad
你还举了个例子
given an example of where (state i will be kept),that is good
那是不是布局管理器就要去全方位的保持其无状态的性质呢
should it be aiming to be fully stateless
最好的实践是将追踪的状态控制在可控范围之内
aim to be fully stateless if you can manage it
就拿我的例子来说明好了,在我写的初版中
so I'll give you an example from the way I built it so the initial implementation that i wrote
我对状态的追踪很重,像说第一可见视图的位置
I track very heavily things like the first visible position
以及整个位置的偏移,我总是保持着对这两个状态的追踪
and that position offset and I kept that state around
那当我开始调用datasetChanged的时候,当我从
all the time and when we started doing dataset changes where we went from
一个很大的grid转到一个很小的grid的时候,
like a really large grid to really small grid or something like that
我尝试着还让这两个状态是有效的
trying to assume that value was even valid anymore
这导致我写了很多if语句.如果我是把视图
lead to a long list if statements.well,if I shifted
给往下平移了话,那么新的位置就要平移回去.
如果往其他方向,同样也要把位置给变回去
all the way down and l need to shift back but if I shifted from here I need to do this
那样做就很麻烦.其实,在此时,如果我执行一次fill的话,
and if I had just basically run a new fill where at that point I say okay
就相当于我对framework说,根据我现在的情况
based on what I've got
你帮我布局出来要看到的视图吧
what am I supposed to be able to see
这就会是一种非常简单的布局流程了.
因此,我的建议是,尽量去对好的状态进行追踪
it would have been a much simpler flow.so I mean as far as good state to track
换一种说法,在实现基本布局管理器的前提下,
唯一我推荐你去追踪的就是
that mean the only thing that I would recommend in a basic implementation you track
对任何将要移动过去的目标位置进行追踪
is any target positions you're moving towards
因此,如果你在做一个线性滚动或者在做scrollToPosition的话,
so if you're doing a linear scroll or if you are doing scroll to position and you're
在进行一次新的布局pass时,你可能不得不去追踪
going to get a new layout pass you kinda have to track
你将要移向的目标位置.
因为这个位置在布局流程中并不会被传递给你
where you wanna go cos that's not passed around for you
但是通常,对于当前的layout里的任何状态
but in general,anything about the current state of the layout
我认为大多数情况下你的布局不应该去依赖这些状态
if you can get away with it and most cases I think you should be able to
你不必去追踪任何东西
you shouldn't have to track anything
如果你要需要在每个列表项上都保存一个状态时
and if you do it as per item
你应该将其保存在ViewHolder中
stick in the view holder
我觉得我们还能再提问一个问题
one more question I think we have time for
噢,你是在说像飞划这种手势么
oh you mean like for fling behavior
onFling什么的并不在布局管理器中
it's not really exposed
因此如果你要去对Fling什么的做自定制的话
so if you were to do it you would have to override the
你就要该去重写RecyclerView的方法了
recycler view itself as well
以及对API进行一些修改.我并没有去这么做过
and kinda modify the API a little bit so I haven't really looked doing it
我只知道这样干是有可能的,
但是并不会去让你对Fling本身进行定制
it would be possible but it's not given to you,that behavior is really
这个行为是在内部处理的,你唯一能获取到的是
define internally the only one when you're given is the
Fling行为整个动画,而Fling内部的行为并不能由用户直接控制
is the animation part of that that's not user directed
好了,谢谢大家,如果大家还有任何问题
alright,well thanks your time,guys.if you have any other questions,
等我站在台下后,我们可以一起再探讨.
i will step off the side here,we can address on that
各位可以鼓掌了